Edward D. Kuekes Cartoons
Edward D. Kuekes Cartoons
1947-1966
Kuekes, Edward D., 1901-1987.
51 linear feet
Papers of the Pulitzer Prize-winning American editorial cartoonist. Collection consists of original drawings created for the Cleveland Plain Dealer (1947-1963) and includes a reproduction of "Aftermath," which won Kuekes the Pulitzer Prize in 1953.
149114
Biographical History
Edward D. Kuekes (1901-1987) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Ed Kuekes was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania on February 2, 1901. He studied at the Baldwin-Wallace College, the Cleveland Institute of Art, and the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts. He was appointed to President Eisenhower's "People to People" committee and has received awards from the Newspaper Guild, the C.I.T. Fund, the Freedom Fund at Valley Forge, and the National Safety Council. He has been presented with the Baldwin-Wallace Alumni Merit Award, the National Cartoonists Society Silver T-Square Award, the United States Presidential Prayer Award, the Christopher Award, the United States Treasury Award, the Salvation Army Centennial Award, and in 1953 the Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Cartooning. He is the creator of Funny Fables and the cartoon Alice in Wonderland for United Features Syndicate, and has lectured to various art groups on the subject, "So you can't draw a straight line, either."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Edward D. Kuekes Cartoons consists of approximately 4,000 original political cartoons which appeared in the Cleveland Plain Dealer between 1947 and 1963. The collection is arranged chronologically. In addition to a few press clippings about Kuekes, the collection also includes a reproduction of "Aftermath," the cartoon for which Kuekes was awarded the 1953 Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Cartooning, as well several other printed examples of Kuekes' work.
Related Material
has collections of over eighty cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Kuekes, Edward D., 1901-1987.; Cleveland plain dealer (Cleveland, Ohio: 1885); Plain dealer (Cleveland, Ohio); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Ohio -- Cleveland.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Pulitzer Prizes.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government, 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Edward D. Kuekes, 1964.
Inventory
- Clippings and Printed Material
  - Newspaper clippings 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed Material 1953-1964, includes "Aftermath" (Kuekes' 1953 Pulitzer Prize winning cartoon), "A Tribute to Winston Churchill", "The Nation Speaks Out for the President" (cover portrait of LBJ by Kuekes), and cartoons memorializing the death of Rachel Carson and the assassination of John F. Kennedy.; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Cartoons
  - 1947-1948 (Oversize 1)
  - 1949 Jan-Feb (Oversize 1)
  - 1949 Mar-Aug (Oversize 2)
  - 1949 Sep-Dec (Oversize 3)
  - 1950 Jan-Apr (Oversize 4)
  - 1950 May-Aug (Oversize 5)
  - 1950 Sep-Dec (Oversize 6)
  - 1951 Jan-Apr (Oversize 7)
  - 1951 May-Aug (Oversize 8)
  - 1951 Sep-Dec (Oversize 9)
  - 1952 Jan-Apr (Oversize 10)
  - 1952 May-Aug (Oversize 11)
  - 1952 Sep-Dec (Oversize 12)
  - 1953 Jan-Apr (Oversize 13)
  - 1953 May-Aug (Oversize 14)
  - 1953 Sep-Dec (Oversize 15)
  - 1954 Jan-Apr (Oversize 16)
  - 1954 May-Aug (Oversize 17)
  - 1954 Sep-Dec (Oversize 18)
  - 1955 Jan-Apr (Oversize 19)
  - 1955 May-Aug (Oversize 20)
  - 1955 Sep-Dec (Oversize 21)
  - 1956 Jan-Apr (Oversize 22)
  - 1956 May-Aug (Oversize 23)
  - 1956 Sep-Dec (Oversize 24)
  - 1957 Jan-Apr (Oversize 25)
  - 1957 May-Aug (Oversize 26)
  - 1957 Sep-Dec (Oversize 27)
  - 1958 Jan-Apr (Oversize 28)
  - 1958 May-Aug (Oversize 29)
  - 1958 Sep-Dec (Oversize 30)
  - 1959 Jan-Apr (Oversize 31)
  - 1959 May-Aug (Oversize 32)
  - 1959 Sep-Dec (Oversize 33)
  - 1960 Jan-Apr (Oversize 34)
  - 1960 May-Aug (Oversize 35)
  - 1960 Sep-Dec (Oversize 36)
  - 1961 Jan-Apr (Oversize 37)
  - 1961 May-Aug (Oversize 38)
  - 1961 Sep-Dec, includes 5 cartoons dated 1961 only (i.e. no month indicated) (Oversize 39)
  - 1962 Jan-Apr (Oversize 40)
  - 1962 May-Aug (Oversize 41)
  - 1962 Sep-Nov (Oversize 42)
  - 1963 Apr-Aug (Oversize 43)
  - 1963 Sep-Dec (Oversize 44)
  - Misc. Undated (Oversize 44)
  - "An Ode to Syracuse University Library Associates" (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Oversize Cartoons
  - 1950 Aug-1956 Aug [OVERSIZE], 62 items (Oversize 45)
  - 1956 Sep-1957 Dec [OVERSIZE], 83 items (Oversize 46)
  - 1958 Jan-1958 Dec [OVERSIZE], 70 items (Oversize 47)
  - 1959 Jan-1959 Dec [OVERSIZE], 73 items (Oversize 48)
  - 1960 Jan-1960 Dec [OVERSIZE], 78 items (Oversize 49)
  - 1961 Jan-1963 Jun [OVERSIZE], 49 items (Oversize 50)